A Guide to the Yount Family Papers, 1808-2011
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Yount Family Papers, 1808-2011
The Library of Virginia
52191
8.95 cu. ft (18 boxes)
Yount Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Tim Abbott, March 2018.
Biographical Information
Joseph Yount (1765-1839) was born in York County Pennsylvania to Swiss immigrant Rudolph Yount and Frances Schaffner Yount. In 1794, Joseph Yount moved to Rockingham County, Virginia, with his parents and two brothers. After his marriage to Elizabeth Bowman in 1798, Joseph bought a farm in Augusta County, where the young couple began to establish their family. Descendants of Joseph Yount include brothers Stephens Russell Yount (1892-1959) and Glenn Ellyson Yount (1893-1968), who both served in the United States Air Service during World War I; Violette Belle Yount (1902-1992), an accomplished artist and songwriter who regularly wrote songs for J. Chas McNeil and Bob Carleton; and Joseph Byron Yount III (1939-2016), a former United States counterintelligence officer who later became the second youngest mayor in Waynesboro's history.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1808-2011, of the Yount Family consist of correspondence, photographs, account books, diaries, school notebooks, and scrapbooks, general papers, newsletters and newspapers, and ephemera. Much of the correspondence, newsletters, and newspapers were sent from Stephens Russell Yount and Glenn Ellyson Yount while they were serving in the military during World War I.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into six series: I. Correspondence, II. Photographs, III. Ledgers, IV. General Papers, V. Newspapers and Newsletters, and VI. Ephemera.
Contents List
- Correspondence,, 1808-2011., Extent: 8 boxes. (Box 1-8)
  Correspondence, 1808-2011, is primarily comprised of letters to and from the Yount family, though some items are written to members of the related Stephens or Pelter family. This series contains various types of correspondence, including both handwritten and typed letters, invitations, postcards, birthday and holiday cards, and several telegrams and emails. Topics include daily life, financial and legal matters, and current events. Much of the correspondence originates from Virginia, with the notable exception of the World War I and II letters, which arrived respectively from France and California. Also included are several folders of empty envelopes.
  Series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence, 1808-1889. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1913. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1919. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1927. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1930. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1934. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1939. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1942. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1952. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1957. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1960. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1961. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1966. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1979. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980-2011. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1917-1918. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1918. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1919. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1919. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1919. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, WWI, 1919 and undated. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, WWII, 1943-1945. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Envelopes, 1888-1954. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Envelopes, 1954-1986 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1955-2005., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 8-9)
  Photographs, 1955-2005, are primarily comprised of photographs of the Ewing family, as well as images of Joseph B. Yount III and his sister JoAnn Yount. Photographs depict men, women, and children at reunions, parties, and graduations, and include a variety of formal and candid images. Also included in this series are two photograph albums.
  - Addie Woods Photograph, undated. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Army Reunion at 611 Photographs, undated. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chuck Perkett Photographs, 1967 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Ewing Army Photographs, undated. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Ewing and Laney Photographs, 1987 and 1994. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Ewing Family Reunion Photographs, undated. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Ewing Photographs, 1987, 2005 and unated. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - JBY and Jerry Balites RMS Photographs, 1955. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - JBY U.S. Army Photographs, undated. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Jim Morgan and Richard Dulaney Photographs, 1991. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Joanne Photographs, 1935 and undated. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - John and Nancy Ewing Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - John Ewing Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - John Ewing Wedding and Reception Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - John Laney Army Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Nancy Ewing Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Paul Williams Photograph, 1987. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Perkett and Army Buddies Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - RMS Grad JBY, 1956. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - RMS Graduation, 1956. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified Group Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Unidentified Men Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Unidentified Women Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - USP Aspen Photographs, undated. (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Ledgers, 1860-1983., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 10-14)
  Ledgers, 1860-1983, include account books, diaries, school notebooks, and scrapbooks. Someof the diaries were written anonymously, while others were written by Yount and Pelter family members. Account books variously detail personal debts and the financial accounts of the Yount family farm. Also included in this series is an undated commercial calculator, an "In Memorium" notebook, and an anonymous notebook containing telephone numbers.
  - Account Book, 1934-1950. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Papers from Account Book, 1934-1950. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Account Ledger, 1860. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Blue Book of Telephone Numbers, undated. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1902. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1925-1927. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Papers from Diary, 1925-1927. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1927-1929. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Papers from Diary, 1927-1929. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Diary, 1929-1932. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Papers from Diary, 1929-1932. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Diary, 1933-1935. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Papers from Diary, 1933-1935. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Diary, 1938-1944. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Papers from Diary, 1938-1944. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Diary, 1941-1945. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1945-1949. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Diary, 1945-1950. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Diary, 1950-1955. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Diary, 1955-1956. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Diary, 1957-1959. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Diary, 1964-1969. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1974-1978. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Papers from Diary, 1974-1978. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Hazel Alice Yount Diary, 1946-1950. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Papers from Hazel Alice Yount Diary, 1946-1950. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Hazel Alice Young Diary, 1979-1983. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Hazel Yount English Notebook, 1924. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "In Memorium" Notebook, undated. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Joe Yount III Notebook, 1972-1974. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Joe Yount III Notebook, undated. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Joe Yount III Notebook, undated. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Mary Welsh Notebook, 1909. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ropp's Commercial Calculator, undated. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Sampson Pelter Notebook, 1951-1955 and undated. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Samuel W. Yount Diary, 1976-1981. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Papers from Samuel W. Yount Diary, 1976-1981. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - School Notebook, undated. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - School Notebook, undated. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Papers from School Notebook, undated. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1942-1981. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, undated. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Violette B. Yount Diary, 1933-1942. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Violette B. Yount Diary, 1950-1954. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Papers from Violette B. Yount Diary, 1950-1954. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Violette B. Yount Diary, 1964-1968. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Papers from Violette B. Yount Diary, 1964-1968. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Yount Farm Account Book, 1980. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- General Papers, 1836-1991 and undated., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 15-17)
  General Papers, 1836-1991, of the Yount family include genealogical research material from Alexandria and Loudon County, numerous contracts and agreements, recipes, programs, newspaper clippings, the copyright registrations of many of Violette B. Yount's songs, speeches written by Joseph B. Yount III, memorandum from the Office of Air Service, as well as numerous miscellaneous writings, notes, and poetry. Also included in this series is some financial and business paperwork of Joseph B. Yount III from his time as city attorney.
  - Accounts, 1836. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1864-1865. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Alexandria, VA Research, undated. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Business and Membership Cards, 1945-1982 and undated. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, 1923 and 1933. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Christmas Lists, 1941-1986. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Christmas Lists, 1942-1982. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Collaboration Agreements, 1939. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - The Congressional Record, 1930-1931. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Contracts, 1842-1946. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Copyright Registrations, 1940-1973. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Descriptive Introductory List #237, undated. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Estate Tax Audit Paperwork, 1974. (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - F + M Check Stubs, 1972. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Genealogical Materials, 1949-1984 and undated. (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Household Inventories, 1977. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Hair, 1890 and undated. (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Illustrations, undated. (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Insurance Paperwork, 1870-1922. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - JBY Speeches, 1977 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - J.R. Balderson, 1933-1940. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Loudoun Co., VA Research, 1954-1967 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Luke McLuke Book, undated. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Materials in French, 1892-1919. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1935-1942. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, WWI, undated. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, undated. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1963-1980 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Obituaries, undated. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Office of Air Service Memos, 1919. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets, 1927-1979 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Pelter Family Research, 1953 and undated. (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Plat of the Lands of J.E. and Katie Fisher, South River District, August Co., VA, 1951. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Poetry, undated. (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Political Materials, 1978. (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Programs, 1924-1975. (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1976-1991. (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Quotes, 1979 and undated. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Railroad Retirement Board, 1961. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and Invoices, 1841-1968. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Receipts, Insurance, 1980-1981. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Recipes, undated. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Richard Stephens Papers, 1858-1864. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Schoolwork, undated. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Scorecards, undated. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Segregationist Materials, undated. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Stationary, undated. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Vehicle Paperwork, 1923-1975. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Warranties, 1977 and undated. (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Waynesboro Public Library Press Release, 1968. (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Newspapers and Newsletters, 1918-1919 and undated., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 17-18)
  Newspapers and newsletters, 1918-1919, include several full editions of the Stars and Stripes newspaper, as well as the unit newsletters of Stephens Russell Yount and Glenn Ellyson Yount from their military service during World War I. These newsletters include "The Hub", "The Mic", "The Steering Wheel", and "The Unit", and detail daily life of servicemen. These newsletters were sent by the Yount brothers from France to their family members in Virginia.
  - "The Hub" Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 1, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - "The Hub" Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 4, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - "The Hub" Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 5, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - "The Hub" Newsletter, Vol. 1, No. 8, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - "The Mic", Unit 306 Newsletter, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Riviera American, No. 1, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 1, No. 38, 1918. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 1, No. 52, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 5, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 7, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 12, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 10, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 9, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 14, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Stars and Stripes, Vol. 2, No. 15, 1919. (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - "The Steering Wheel" Newsletter, Vol. 2, No. 5, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - "The Unit" Newsletter, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - "The Unit" Newsletter, Vol. 2, 1919. (Box 17, Folder 21)
- Ephemera, undated., Extent: 1. (Box 17)
  Ephemera, undated, of the Yount family is comprised of a wooden lid, a pocket day timer, and the trench mirror of Stephens Russell Yount from his service during World War I.
  - Lid, undated. (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - Pocket Day Timer, undated. (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - Trench Mirror, undated. (Box 17, Folder 24)